hello welcome back and welcome to the
video here with you honest listening to
the logos and it's also say listening
with and logos as well and I'll give
some context on the conversation after
some housekeeping so the one of the main
things is is we're open for registration
for the next part of circling course
which is basis is essentially what we
were just having a conversation about
with you Hannes the deeper underpinnings
or sensibility that it is circling and
and the deeper
I'd say trans rational sense of
listening so if you're interested in
being trained in that we the art of
circling is online so if you're no
longer bound to location so we're doing
it on zoom and it's working out quite
well but we are open for registration
we just finished a course this weekend
we also have weekend courses I think the
next one is is in like a month or so and
then we also have drop-in evenings
3-hour events from 7:00 to 10:00 p.m. on
zoom' so I'll put the links for all that
below also if you're interested in
working one-on-one with me please email
me and my emails below as well okay so
the context of this conversation with
Johannes is is really something excuse
me is specifically about my part of a
anthology that you Hannes and myself and
Jennifer baekje
and Chris and a bunch of people that
we've all been talking to about Dial
logos so what I was interested in
talking with Johannes about was this
sense of of logos and listening right
and what I've been through writing in
this
academic kind of style which is new for
me in itself is revealing but it's also
in investigating this really seeing how
deeply what is happening encircling what
defines it as distinct from say
psychology or sociology I or any of the
kind of humanities there's something
very different going on right and it
lies in its basic come from ontological
II and so it's really interesting this
paper is revealing a lot to me about
what I've already been doing things I've
always suspected but in a with a rigor
to it or a sense of rigor to it so
Johanna said I talk a lot about logos
about listening about forge in future
right what is the difference between
listening to a cartesian subject and
listening to design or being there and
and listening not to the logos or not to
them not not to the speaker but the
logos what does that mean right what's
going on there what does that reveal
so I really enjoyed this conversation
and I hope you do as well you can please
like the video if you enjoy it also you
can subscribe to my channel if you want
to see all the upcoming videos and have
a good day thank you so the one of the
things you know would be you and I are
both working on a anthology contribution
and about dialo goes with a bunch of the
people that we've been talking with and
so my my part of it is well a couple of
things one is I'm actually realizing
just the process of writing this way is
so interesting because the writing leads
into seeing more of what I'm actually
writing about which has the last
paragraph end up being the first one
right there's this kind of this is re
it's very her bette hermetic in that
sense um but I'm seeing how deeply
actually my work encircling how deeply
it is really about about logos and about
listening and and essentially and I like
this word that I've been getting from
your your reading from your teacher
about non-contingent see like the
non-contingent in that ring of sense
that happens when you're not relating to
somebody as a as a somebody or the world
as something you're having to deal with
for the sake of something else right but
this sense of listening as his
Heraclitus says which is just it's
really fresh right now cuz I just got
done reading that the chapter on logos
this one this book a couple of times
yeah so it's really it's like a ringing
true but precisely this this
this sense in which were here classes
you know do not listen to me listen to
the logos okay
is that cool - GU yes that like one I
want to talk a little bit about what the
difference is right between listening
let's say to the logos right versus you
could say a more techniques in s-- right
of listening to a subject right a
Cartesian subject and so there's that
there's there's that that piece and I
think one of the things I'm kind of
realizing through working this out is
you know really seeing how the
difference that lies within what I'm
doing and circling is is is so different
it's it's different not necessarily in
content but it's precisely different in
from like so cuz because it looks a lot
like something in psychology or
something out of the self-help movement
or something like that it can look a lot
like that however it isn't it isn't that
and I'm starting to realize in a more
precise way why it's not that it's
because it's a very different it's a its
purpose is very very different
its purpose is actually to ring to hear
this like to dive into the sense of what
is and where as psychology there's or
sociology has a sense in which it's it
seems to presuppose like sociology or
associate the a sociology being
something that the subject becomes but
I'm kind of I'm realizing that actually
this it contends with a completely
different understanding that isn't is it
sociological in that sense but rather in
some way being is already social right
there's a
like the sense of being with and I think
Heidegger talks a lot about this of like
you know to be with you know you're
always already being with and this being
with is similar to the being in
structure of the way that of our way of
being in the world and so there is this
kind of sense where it's like
relationship not as what I think is now
today super super super hyper present
through social social media which is a
sense where you relationship is about
getting related it's about having
connections right like you have your
Facebook friends and it's it's you get
this thing called connection
which i think is actually it seems to me
that that's really based on a whole set
of cartesian positive you know positing
points you're a point in which i then
connect with you and then i have this
connection with you but encircling the
the whole the whole practice is that
were were there what makes it what it is
is is to dwell on the question of how
deeply can we be with what is how
profoundly can we be with what is and
i'm starting to realize that through
reading this and especially around non
contingency the sense of um the sense of
the sense of the moment not being
contingent on a bunch of things right
now something i'm dealing with but
rather something that you can become
aware of so in other words like there's
a way in which relationship is something
we can become aware of the way in which
we're already related and that already
related right brings us into a like a
non like starts to get i think starts to
speak into the logos so in the in the
paper I'm kind of like I'm I'm I'm
looking at I'm looking at the socio
sociological sub positions right and and
then seeing seeing how that dip like it
and watching it kind of them fall
apart in some way and it's revealing
more of what we're doing so I think I
what I'd love to do is just talk a
little bit about and hear your thoughts
about what it is it like what a couple
dicks the logos right why
is it about the logos that seems to be
so appropriate to hearing to listening
and what is it when I listen to the
logos and not you who are you
right who's the you right who's me and
kind of in a certain sense in
distinction from a couple of things I
don't talk right and except starting to
think about like rethinking and
reformulating or re seeing the the the
sense of authenticity right that isn't
about in some sense being who I really
am or something like that it's more it's
much deeper it seems to be the way that
the sense of my relationship to the
sense of being and I want to talk a
little bit about like that said that but
not knowing being but the sense of being
right and what that what that speaks to
is long mm-hmm Heidegger has the spiel
but Heidegger briefly years he worked
with psychiatrist psychologist for 10
years some of what was spoken about
during that time in Switzerland which
was from the 50s to the 60s it's
published as the Sala Kahn seminars and
what apparently always seemed most
outrageous to the participating
psychiatrists and psychologists was to
give up on the boards now in the
vernacular called Cartesian paradigm we
have to be of course but careful also we
have to keep questioning also what do we
actually mean by Cartesian paradigm
or Cartesian subjectivity it's become a
bit of a boogeyman I think that's being
thrown around everywhere and there's a
really perpetrator right well yeah but
there's a necessity there's a necessity
to Descartes also yeah and the what's
dangerous in general with reading
someone like hi again is that one you
know we could easily perhaps begin to
think that oh you know his system
it's just blaming all of metaphysics for
not getting it right but now look at him
he's coming along or no but obviously
something happened with DES kind which
is an incision it's the beginning of
modernity for a specific reason that's
his name which which has to do with what
with the freedom that Descartes takes in
his thinking I to cast doubt on
everything in this manner which is which
is a form of negativity of negation is
taking a very autonomous stance it has
of course it bears within itself another
it has another issue which is that it
neglects the negativity of its own being
this subject which is why hiding a
response to it by saying resume movie
bull moose I am insofar as I'm towards
my death that's very early Heidegger but
there's a necessity to Descartes and and
so that you know it's it's it's kind of
day card if he the day card is
responding to something as well and that
is the necessity of of a freedom that
begins to unfold in modernity now on the
logos it's you mentioned Heraclitus
fragment b50 is
the following book EMU is ancient Greek
okay
EMU Allah - logu aku Santa's kimono game
stop honest in him panting I we only
have the fragment but the first two
words are hook a Mook means no or not
they move to me not to me having not to
me so it's you see even here there is
not subjectivity but there is not an ego
either but there is there is a self
referentiality but one that negates
itself
look EMU not to me
Allah but to logu to logos hmm is the
enchanted form of logos I think aku
Santa's having listened I could react
even the word acoustics from a cool I
hear that's a participle form and after
having listened or while were through
listening to logos homologue aim to say
stuff honest in then it's wise to say so
phone Sofia Philadelphia then it's wise
to say and Hunter a knight at one is
many hmm look my this is perhaps
relevant that there is the there is her
Heraclitus addresses himself but at the
same time negates himself and then
points to logos and now you can I would
think that a precise interpretation
would would be to say that it needs the
the medium of of the human being to
speak itself so it's it's the logos
through in this case Heraclitus that
speaks through him insofar as
he is gathered I'm on it hmm hmm and
then we could say had ponte a night one
yeah well so okay so just right there
so listening to you yeah it's funny
there was a way were you I was noticing
you in a certain sense went more into
the background as I'm listening to what
you're saying right and then when you
stopped there was a sense of you
gathered back right there's this so just
even just right in that exchange right
there there was that sense of well the
one actually the one and the many the
one here in this census what does that
kind of Tate was that oh I lost your
sound that that's the question mm-hmm
maybe we can't so we shouldn't just say
what is the one and the it that's the
maybe what what can be said is that this
is what has to be thought perhaps the
the one is the beginning and the origin
and then it habit it has to be thought
it has to be explicated in thought right
so one of one of the things that we try
to do in modernity is we try to we try
to look but just to give some some
breadcrumbs right some hints in modality
we try to solve problems we so by the
way problem is Greek kept problema and
means cliff and it also means a riddle
and it also means loser and tremana
solutions and it means something like a
riddle a maze that bears
in itself already its solution but and
we'd have to get into the etymology of
the word too but when when analytical
philosophers look at can't what they try
to do is they see a problem for example
calm as you know runs into the
antinomies of reason you know reason can
say two completely different can make
two complete different claims for
example the world is infinite it has no
beginning and no ending and this is what
went enemies and and and the opposite
would be as a precise beginning in a
precise ending and the reason can argue
for it now a and then further down he
going you get into cons for example he
runs into these dialectical problems
which he doesn't appreciate how you get
to Hegel I mean you look at it from the
standpoint of analytical philosophy work
then it tries to solve these problems by
bringing in for example is it just one
example in the ethical philosophy a
third self who tries to be correct right
it tries to be right it tries to be
right yeah and so when when we're
looking at a a thinker like Heraclitus
quizzes who's obviously extremely free
right in his when you the more you read
of him it's someone who thinks not you
know then this terms of free thinkers we
think of it today but there's a
tremendous autonomy in this in this
thought the business there's a because
there's no burden yet or yeah two and a
half thousand years of obvious tended of
a very long today aside here calls it
somewhere so the today yeah yeah long
today yeah and and the the the third one
is many or that out of many one a
pluribus unum by the way which he had in
your constitution in the u.s. too
is is one that sustains what we've come
to call the oxidant when such things
alright thought and it always comes back
to this you can even read de can't when
you talk the the ego cogito these
self-referential as we now call the self
referential ego they feel the things of
itself yes perhaps related to the one
and then coming back out to the many
maybe that's taking a little bit too
liberally but this thought off that
there can be one that there can be many
at the same time sustains the history
so-called off of Occidental philosophy
and now in terms of the the listening
yeah I make this claim about logos it's
because in what's now the specified as
fragment one is that this logos here its
meaning to the looting etc we are to
something we are always listening but
we're not really or kind of hearing it
but not really listening to it that's
how you couldn't translate perhaps this
first fragment so there's a forgetting
he actually speaks of lon tunnel of
forgetting towards the end of the the
passage and so the the this relationship
with logos as many fold as it is
explicate 'add is one apparently
according to Heraclitus of listening now
of course you could ask well what what
is this what does this mean but then
maybe you could say a bits about what
would elicit what what well about the
experience of listening
well there's a couple things what I said
thought that when he's talked about yeah
perhaps it's important that we not solve
the problem of the question what is one
great it dissolved in that sense is that
related to solvent do you know and
what's that like to solve a problem is
that that is it the same derivative as
solvent like that word just because
that's one of the big things that comes
in the way if so I think in terms of
listening right actually is
problem-solving it's it's really weird
like oh yeah solving in the sense of
this solving yeah yeah it's just that I
just thought what do you know it is that
is is is it the same etymology or root
do you know it should be and it's
probably from solute seal in Latin and
the Greek an allele which is the root
for and the mythical means also I
dissolve right right so the analysis is
important because it helps to dissect to
really you know single out and look at
something specifically you think of
medicines rather important you know
where you where you cut someone open
exactly but the these analytic II Anna
if we stay with the purely analytical
you are the sole thing I think for the
most part yeah and then you make yeah
cuz I that's one of the ways that I
think I've noticed we're listening often
at least with each other we're listening
often stops right yeah is when you know
you're listening to somebody and you
know somebody starts to reveal something
about themselves and somebody's jumps in
to start solving the problem for them or
giving advice but there's a there's a
way where it seems like that's right
we're listening stops and I think one of
the things that you just did
is when you said this was also
interesting how he heard this was was
yes important we not perhaps solved the
problem of the one yeah but actually he
said start to in a certain sense what I
heard was start to reveal the origin and
what's interesting is like all of a
sudden I noticed that put the origin
into somehow into the future and
listening to it right like the the sense
of origin yeah and that tuning a tooth
like being a tomb to it and in some way
attuned to by it
that's the I think that there's that
quality of whatever it is that doesn't
doesn't solve the one but listens to it
right listens to it which I think means
starting to hear the ring yeah of the
origin right and a tuning to that
there's a sense in which here's like a
this is Heidegger I really could set
this he's like um rich Texas this this
is on the on the way to language it's a
diet yeah if the dialogue with the
Japanese philosophers is um this is part
actually says the Japanese person says
we Japanese do not think it's strange if
a dialogue leaves undefined what is
really intended or even restores it back
to the keeping of the undefinable then
higher says this is part I believe of
every dialogue that has turned out well
between thinking beings as if of its own
accord it can take care that this
undefinable something not only does not
slip away but displays its gathering
force evermore luminously in the course
of the dialogue
so there's a there's this kind of
quality to the what I hear and that is
it's it's a very similar sense of like
well perhaps we should just not like
throw a bunch of solvent on to the this
question of the one right but actually
and what in what way is it listen to it
it is this this urge to solve yeah you
can see this in in in the in this
discourse on the meta-crisis yeah right
so i facetiously and said provocatively
have said there will be a meta-crisis
meta-crisis yeah let's say I've been
saying I said because I said it's like
propping up on my Twitter feed people
talk about the meta-crisis I mean I can
it get said something that's real it
gets on something that's true which is
there is a profound crisis and mind you
that crisis is modernity itself because
modernity itself is the proper the
programmatic denial which is itself
indication both the negativity of being
and at the same time trying to at the
same time as the fundamental
presupposition of thought namely the
unity between being and thought has
withdrawn this identity and listen this
is what the the mental crisis
I should refer to if it refers to
anything but that is that's the problem
of modernity itself in in a bit of a
simplified nutshell and any kind of
attempt to solve this will lead to yeah
will lead to an infinite regress at
infinitum it cannot find a ground
because it is not in the business of
grounding but in the business of
abstract problem solving according to
you know setting parameters finding
conditions boom here
you go here's a perfect blueprint world
which is one way in which the and it's
interesting by the way just to make this
not to jump around too much but hiding a
actually called psychology psycho
technology so it's very close to him for
to technique a to to is sort of her not
sort of but to really am that an attempt
to control the contents and the desires
of the psyche and by the way control
goes in many directions right and that
doesn't just mean self-control it can
also be external control and one could
think of perhaps of psychology as a sort
of a programmatic attempt to contain
what now some people refer to as you
know Charlie first as the meaning crisis
or nihilism all the meta crisis it's
trying to contain this right I don't
know it's just your personal problem and
it's just your your daddy was mean to
you or it's just maybe you know I've
said there's not to to let me talk about
this off the record some time but it
what a depression perhaps shows or
melancholy shows is perhaps something
much more profound than just some
personal issues
yeah and the the weird so here's the
weird thing that needs to be worked out
so this is just too much of a slogan but
the
that I can't do this just on the top of
my hat but here's the strange thing is
that be at the empty attempted abstract
problem-solving do actually not think
there is no thinking because with
thinking has to it has to explicate
itself and this and here's what you know
because we look at philosophy it's as
something that's now an installer sized
file over here you've got your your your
philosophy section it's really
interesting but if you take me too
seriously then thoughts and come and
dust it guide the world and back we're
back with you know the the stillness
here too there is a need to listen to
silent movements in history in order to
understand what what's what's going on
and let's not underestimate what what
happens in what we now call the journey
therapy with Hume the unity between
being in thought collapses conned sees
through this dogmatic skepticism then
the this presupposition which has also
led to a dogmatic philosophy which then
only a couple of decades after count
didn't speak to anyone anymore
I mean you know the Leibniz in Wilkin
proofs of God etc there was a world that
died a little speaks of a new world
being born as he as he wrote the
feminazi of spirit and the the attempt
of thinkers like Karl
Victor shelling Hegel each in a
different way is to establish again this
unity or let's say identity of being and
thought because in a non dogmatic way in
order to achieve what to achieve the
self certainty that human beings also
require Heidegger will come to call this
you know the belonging together of being
and thought but with this access split I
think that's what the what may be the
meta-crisis get
that without really being able to to see
it fully and then trying to solve it at
once but the the response shouldn't be
to try to let's get all the models right
right um and then we can we can we can
just pull it over the world and make it
work according to the solution we've
come up with but we had we have to
solution explicate these faults and we
have to wonder also why is it that
Heraclitus still speaks to us why is it
that Plato still speaks to us and it's
in I think it's here after this you know
somewhat of a completion or self
fulfillment um that maybe thinking
begins again and as you know Heidegger
listens to to language for example
meeting please think of highly Heidegger
listens to words yeah yeah we've talked
about the I admit in the seminar last
week yeah right the this weird way of
listening to a word of course this has
of course an inherent danger which is a
key that maybe it just becomes arbitrary
right that that's it's so it's this is a
very hairy subject only well I can
actually I can I can imagine I just got
this sense of like live nits and can't
and then Hegel
on some sense they was responding to
something right yeah right like they're
done some level I think a lot of people
think right that you know each think are
kind of like thought of this thought
newly or something right posited
something or invented something but it
my understanding is it they're they're
tuned into something right like so it's
like this sense of that some world had
died right in some sense called that
death was perhaps what Hegel was
responding to as always listening to on
some level right yes and and you see the
this this attempt to solve it so obvious
so obviously when everything is a crisis
right
here here's a headline for you this is
one headline everything everything but
everything is in crisis yeah um and but
why what what this crisis mean you know
and so not to become too arbitrary and
say Oh crisis means this in ancient
Greek blah blah so this is how we should
think of it the the question should
become well first of all how you know
crisis and critique news can't are
related these two words are related
renamed means to distinguish to
differentiate and the the attempt and so
what what met there is a response by the
discourse of meta-crisis true a certain
crisis and meta I think is supposed to
indicate that it's on a level that's not
just purely concrete so we can't just
look at the financial crisis the
economic crisis the housing crisis etc I
think that's what this is trying to get
at um but if the response is an
immediate attempt to solve which is the
extremely you know high
modern which is again what which is the
denial of the negativity of being yeah
yeah yeah which which is the denial of
non controllability which is a denial of
non availability the funny thing is I
can only say this by doing what by by
constantly speaking actually off and or
in terms of negative negate negating
right the Nile is in the gating yeah not
available it's it's this negations
double negations etc that I was drawing
and you're concealing yeah and then I
think so the the the travel comes in
where it's just one model is supposedly
replaced by another model yeah and and
so the you know the sense of listening
which would require what an initial
openness that could ignite something
right and we ask something like what
what are we like what what do we what's
being said in the withdrawal right yeah
is actually take up the to actually in a
certain sense be with right or notice
and listen to the negativity right so
this so the the the trouble with with
with scientific models in general is
that they are constructing constructing
a world without contradictions or a
model a model is always without
contradiction it mustn't contain a
contradiction now one could promote it
if we say or whenever you deny
contradiction it comes back to haunt you
and in you you actually it you one
cannot get rid of contradiction in the
Hegel solution aha I made a mistake
Hegel's response I should say a response
not solution Hegel's response is
dialectics which shows that the world is
both infinite and finite
we are as finite beings infinite in our
finitude insofar as we are individuals
and as such unique and this uniqueness
is our eternity this is the way to
reduced by means of this shouldn't be
quoted on it but hiding it does some
hiding approach this differently
Heidegger approaches opposites in a way
that they are all at once allowed right
it's always about the similar to nation
and once allowed yes Oh at once allowed
I like that the my example would be
Oasis you say places you cannot oh there
is no places without the desert yeah the
oasis in the desert the desert is not
just around it yeah the diocese is in
the desert all right all right so you
have to listen to this this is listed or
listening to listen to listen to the
word Grace's and when want it on how it
unfolds it means to already already
understand or not understand but already
allow for allow for the simultaneity of
desert and Oasis insofar as Nueces can
only be in a desert alright so we're
back with the hanpan tonight and
importantly I think with the with the
listening to come back to this also is
is the the first word again but in in
the fragment t-54 Heraclitus is look
look emu not to me
so not yeah me you know but not to me
but so the there is there is a self
that's that's referring to itself yeah
but it's but it's negating its center
its it
instead you see and NDB beop of course
now it's it's it's the opposite now
there's no solution is here I yeah I've
made you this solution for this problem
well this is not often I'm really
appreciating I'm really appreciating
kind of like just what the I mean what
the what does common straight like
just in this conversation what I'm
getting that ring of its demonstrating
right the very thing that we're talking
about is the very thing that's happening
right on some level like so so as we're
talking and I'm have like listening to
it another in view it's so this is one
of the things that I've always it's
always been such a riddle to me right
where so and I've just come to realize
that this is whatever is going on with
this is so it seems to be really
important or central to people and it's
this experience of people call and they
experience a lot encircling right and
you know probably deep relationships
where the experience of being deeply
they feel deeply see and when they say
they feel deeply seen there's inherent
in it this kind of recognition that I've
been somehow seem deprived right but
what's interesting about it is it's I've
noticed
is it it's listening to the person and
not actually it's actually saying what
seems to be on some level true for them
but they can't they have not been able
to come put into words and then you say
the thing that they didn't say and then
they feel see and I think what that
starts to get at is something about
listen not to me
right but the logos well what is it to
listen to somebody speak I think what it
is is that on some level it's not
listening to the it's it's to listen
what they're thinking right is being
attuned by right it is in response to so
listening to them is actually listening
to on some level what the testimony of
what the possibilities or whatever it is
that's before them right so it's giving
that is getting them right it's it's in
a strange way now on some level
well what it's a in a certain sense it's
like well you start to hear what must
already be what must they be before and
occupied with in responding to such that
they would say the thing that they're
sitting in the way that they're saying
and all of a sudden it starts you start
to hear
what they're in some sense they're not
saying but what they're in response to
and it's when you start to articulate
that when that starts to be said then
they have this experience of being
deeply seen and so it but in that sense
it's not what heilige would call a
psyche know I saw a psycho technology
no because because of psycho technology
just from the sound of it would suggest
that we are dealing with what we are
dealing with something mechanical oh
yeah when this this is it with something
Billy or like a non-contingent it's like
as deep I love this word contingency
it's funny like I've never the way the
heat the evo de janeiro talks about the
non-contingent or the unconditioned
right yeah of that is those moments it
feels like they're they're not it you
haven't solved anything right you're not
at the level of like problem solving
there's this kind of your revoking on
some level this it's you know what it is
it's like you're on some level you're
presencing what is all yet what is
already the case right and all it
already was the case right so it's in
that sense it's not the technology no no
because the technology would would -
well um what would deal with the human
being as if it was a machine and
rearrange certain parts in order to make
make it functional again right and then
and then it's like extract out the
energy from it right yeah
listening would be like you have a
plunger you know yeah yeah and so it
it's it's into hiding again there's the
sense of poiesis perhaps
of of a bringing forth yeah is that what
is that what place this means is it
bringing forth yeah yeah yeah instead of
like a cheese it's like in Tec Tec nay
in this sense would be kind of a
challenging forth a challenging and the
yes the challenging an depositing yeah a
challenging positive the patient comes
to the the psychiatrist with problem
acts and is then classified as case why
and then can use you know Bissonnette
meds and whatever and rearrangement of
their neurological structure in order to
arrive at desired outcome which is
modeled upon what's a pre desired
outcome that that's produced basically
right and and and and the more people
like go the better because the more
material you have to evaluate and to
compare against each other right so it's
it it needs itself and then you know but
there's also of course when the trouble
and this is what's so frightening about
modernity is that anything can become a
cycle technology right
meditation can become one you can have
an app that tells you the to calm down
before you fall asleep so there's this
extreme drive to make everything
available positive yeah and and but it's
all challenged forth right you you can't
can you
and and force the the five-minute
slowdown every evening just to sleep
more efficiently or effectively whatever
the word feat in order to be more
productive to the next day it's it's
it's it's it's turning around itself and
it never actually
and it doesn't allow for what's what it
supposedly does which is listening to
oneself and listening when do you can
you can understand this book a move
maybe also another way right not to not
to me but but listen to what is being
said listen not to me not don't listen
to how I listen to what what is yeah I
said in and also this in this perhaps
and is a dialogue you know between
thinkers perhaps also be didn't circling
and also in a relationship perhaps
because it's it's in it's not not to me
but but listen now to what's at stake
please listen to what is at stake and
not to me there's something at stake and
that thing it's like if there's a sense
of where I get something in in some
sense that kind of an ecstatic its
speaking from the future the origin
speaking from the future there's
something about that sense of it yes I
could going yeah yeah yeah and that you
can't because in some level to just to
listen to okay so do not listen to a
like a subject that's I'm gonna optimize
or posit or something but to listen to
decide right being there is that some
level is to is to listen to them is to
listen to what's there what's a tune a
tuning to them and they're tuned into
such that they're that that which
which glows on the horizon as their
origin right is the origin of their
speech as the origin of their behavior
as the origin of all the things that's
going on so on some level it's listening
to the neck the negativity of that which
withdrawals from them but when you
there's something about but what this is
what's interesting is if there's
something about dia dia logos right like
through right to see area to see through
on some level I get that sense dude not
to me
right but in a certain sense through the
logos the dia right it becomes
transparent in that in that way yeah
this is what this is what I'm saying
it's a for the ontology that we're
writing for what I'm my paper is
entitled to memory as a path through
meaning and one of the things I say
about academic writing is that it's
forgotten what commentary is which is
commentary to think with we have a very
superficial understanding of commentary
which is I think I call this this by the
way here so here's a quote from Tom
Donna Bruner just pull up showdown of
Bruno Miami sauce thinker the
Peripatetic so the Aristotelian zuv old
understand that the end of an action the
Telos it's in the past in the origin in
the future and he says this in a work
entitled the embrace Edie Adam of the
shadows of ideas and shadows he tries to
understand as participation of light and
darkness
so yeah it's you know these these
thoughts have been there um and it would
be it would be good to see where kind of
you know modernity itself splits perhaps
yeah
trajectory because the Oddie's
Renaissance thinkers like Bruno and and
da Vinci who think in terms of shadows
light and darkness yeah
and then of course there's the more a
movement that's more focused on just
bringing light and enlightenment and the
lights of reason to shine upon the world
forgetful of darkness by the way cond is
a is a an elf clear Ghana and
enlightener because he enlightens
thought about this presupposition of the
unity of between being a thought but the
yeah now getting into Karl again but
being it is it let's stay on the future
perhaps forbid I think this is the in
the temporality that comes with the
thought of thousand is is is is already
I mean if if it's in if the origin is in
the future maybe you can say bit more
what what this is supposed to mean
but that does suggest a certain openness
so rather than close it's the it's the
openness that calls me to walk toward it
and I think that's the kind of for
example like there's so I haven't
thought at all I have none of my none of
my libido or my design is thought about
walking through this wall right
however if you could if we somehow in
this conversation you can have we can
have the possibility that it's possible
walk that through that wall to be to
open up for me it's probably all I'll be
thinking about afterwards right so it
seems like what I'm thinking about when
I'm occupy what I'm concerned about is
already on some level speaks to me as a
as as a possibility right and so all of
my all of the things that I may talk
about in my life right on some level
there's this way were you kind of like
you know you know what everyone knows
with this like it's like you you get on
some level you get so bound up in the
content of everything going on that the
that the very thing that has it show up
for you right as the thing to deal with
also the thing that conceals right
conceals the possibility that's ringing
through it and so on some level
listening I think when you when you like
one another another listens with you you
you bring the other brings the other
brings something that you it seems like
you can't bring which is unfamiliarity
right so I think there's something about
bringing if there's something about like
oh it's like when when we go into
dialogue I bring the fact that I bring
my other nacinda sense of the thing that
you can't bring to yourself which is
unfamiliarity
and then all of a sudden you can hear
for example you can hear you know when
you go
maybe people go really you can get this
when you go on vacation and then you
come back to your house and you realize
your house has a scent right and you can
he walk in you're like oh I've been not
smelling that smell in the house like
the whole time I've lived here and I
went away and I brought back my you
could say my unfamiliarity with it and I
can smell what was closest into it yeah
there's it I think there's something
like that Quebec also goes on in the in
the dialog with somebody else is that it
reveals it brings familiarity that
allows the thing that's concealed to
glisten right and that's the experience
of when people it's the it's it's when
their origin during a certain sense the
other speaks with the what you yourself
can't speak but the other says right
that there's this kind of resting back
into okay right yeah the origin right in
some way so yeah I think listening is so
much about listening to what on some
level the possibilities that that you
care about right where they call to you
or the the likelihood right as Mookie
Skype that which likes us and as such
addresses us as hide against the Zionist
as nuclear dust designs of being itself
is that which addresses us as loving and
in this sense you know to hear here's
another here's another headline steel
another headline thinking is only just
beginning one of the one of the
experiences of the guards he is and this
is why they cut is important right but
we have to be careful and I'm not
innocent but we have to be careful you
know they con
he messed it all up for us yeah the they
can't this will to freedom this extreme
autonomy this it is itself an origin but
two cards down and everything is with
loss optically speaking an origin and
it's a question can they be n origin or
it's it's just one origin so that's a
bit difficult but but it is it is let's
say it is a beginning not an origin it
is a beginning it is an onset of
something
it is another beginning in and it's
perhaps it was necessary precisely
because of the burden off the tradition
and this is what philosophy has to do it
has to critique its own tradition and
then however bring it back in and
perhaps for us now for those who engage
in thinking it's the thought should be
that the origin lies in the future and
that which is to come because the other
projects are as you know you know either
critical or just destructive right right
out but if and and then the and then if
the origin lies in the future then it's
more important than there anything else
to listen to those who have thought yeah
and in this at the end this is on the
grand scale of of what philosophy is or
isn't they were thinking is or isn't and
but I think it you know if all of this
is somehow hanging together then this
happens on an individual person levels
as well right right in it when you said
I just got a it made me kind of quiver a
little bit let me said these this way
that being likes us right I just
I just got that sense of like oh yeah
there is this quality of it's so it's so
interesting because I've had the hardest
time understanding the experience is so
pronounced that when those moments of
Alethea ray of origin something speak
there are these moments of profound love
right it really has this quality of like
and on some level like it seems to
always be a love it isn't it isn't like
I love you or you love me it's more like
love the atoms of the air turn to love
it's more like this a tuning this is a
tuning presence and when I thought about
that I was like oh yeah like so on some
level
when the listener hears the origin and
speaks the origin and we start to listen
to like that that is a moment of
revealing that which likes you right
through revealing you because on some
level that which loves you is that which
cut like shapes your face if you will is
a history of you looking at the one who
likes you right
thank you
most kindly so you think you recent I
really enjoy thank you I have to run for
today I'm afraid but we'll continue this
great I think yeah I'd really yeah I'd
really like to continue especially on on
may be more focused on on listening and
on a difference between psychology and
circling yeah let's do that
good I see you Sunday
okay you got it for my sermon like that
nice design with you yeah within moments
I always love those moments were like
that this helped my dog got so big I
lost my sign for a second I have to I
have to I have to write this talk for
for Wednesday I'm the meta-crisis sir
this is what I'm doing their own oh it's
great
want they caught in calling soon yeah
all right well let's stow on I'll great
I look forward to I would look forward
to listening to it maybe I'll go to it
which which one
when is it Wednesday 5:00 p.m. UK time
since the same time we started this
today okay cool yeah I'll just show up
and just lurk lurk yes ask Cartesian
questions of you yes I actually wouldn't
mind yeah yeah yeah okay thank you sir
okay bye